Curriculum Vitae et Studiorum



Personal information

Name and surname
Date and place of birth
Nationality
Gender
Telephone - IT
Telephone - US
email
email
Website
LinkedIn

Michele Scipioni

September 12, 1989, Macerata (MC), Italy Italian

M

+39 320 2475453

+1 (617) 505 9172

michele.scipioni@ing.unipi.it scipioni.michele@gmail.com

http://mscipio.github.io

 $\verb|https://it.linkedin.com/in/scipionimichele| (check for more details about me)|$



Cover section

For the last 2 years, I have done extensive research in the field emission tomography kinetic modeling, with a particular focus on direct estimation of parametric maps from raw PET data. During my master thesis, and my current Ph.D. research, I dealt with non-linear optimization problems, development of mathematical models, and blind source separation. I have also gained some experience in quality management in nuclear medicine, use of workstations (GE Discovery PET/CT and Siemens mMR PET/MR) for acquisition, reconstruction and processing of NM data, and management protocols for storage and retrieval of patient data.

After earning my Ph.D., I am interested in continuing my experience in the academic world, looking for a position (postdoc, research assistant) focused on analysis and modeling of biomedical or biological system. I would love to go on working in the field of image reconstruction and metabolic characterization of medical images, particularly exploring the mutual advantages of combining different imaging modalities, like PET and MRI. I would also welcome, anyway, the possibility to change the current focus of my research, with the aim to find a stimulating working environment, where I could have chance to go on learning both from colleagues, and daily challenges.

Current position(s)

Dates

Name of the employer Position

Principal subjects (keywords)

January 2017 - present

The MGH/HST Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging, Charlestown, MA Graduate Research Assistant

Positron emission tomography; kinetic modeling of radio tracers; aiding tomographic reconstruction with kinetic modeling ind dPET and DCE-MRI; GPU-CUDA parallel programming; Gaussian-Mixture models for PET image segmentation; machine learning.

Dates

Name of the employer Position

Principal subjects (keywords)

November 2015 - present

University of Pisa - Department of Information Engineering Ph.D. student

Positron emission tomography; kinetic modeling of radio tracers; direct methods for the creation of parametric maps; direct segmentation of dPET images in sinogram domain; Bayesian blind source separation of PET dataset.

Work experience

Dates

Name of the employer Type of business or sector Position held

Main activities or responsibilities

October 2016 - December 2016

Department of Information Engineering (DII) at University of Pisa

University department

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Teaching assistant for a Biomedical Imaging class for graduate biomedical engineering students. Topics: iterative reconstruction algorithms for emission tomography (ML-EM and OS-EM); PET kinetic modeling; solution of ODE systems and non linear curve fitting in Matlab

ess Largo Lazzarino 1 - Pisa (PI), Italy

Address

Dates

May 2015 - December 2015

Name of the employer Type of business or sector

Fondazione CNR/Regione Toscana "Gabriele Monasterio" (FTGM), Pisa

Position held

Biomedical research institute

Main activities or responsibilities

Quality management in nuclear medicine; use of workstations for acquisition, reconstruction and processing of NM data; management of the methods of storage and retrieval of data in NM; acquisition of basic knowledge of the techniques for kinetic analysis of dynamic PET sequences.

Address

via G. Moruzzi, 1 - Pisa (PI), Italy

Dates

October 2014 - April 2015

Name of the employer Type of business or sector

Department of Information Engineering (DII) at University of Pisa

University department Position held

Intern

Master thesis student

Main activities or responsibilities

I have done an extensive research in the field of direct estimation of kinetic parameters from dynamic PET acquisitions, researching, implementing, and testing an algorithm of this class, and thus coming to the writing of the thesis for my master degree.

Address

Via G. Caruso 16 - Pisa (PI), Italy

Dates

July 2011 - December 2011

Name of the employer Type of business or sector Position held

University department

Main activities or responsibilities

Bachelor thesis student Definition of a protocol for measuring sEMG signal on a sample of volunteers; acquisition of laboratory measurements; processing and analysis of results; writing of the bachelor thesis.

Department of Information Engineering (DII) at Università Politecnica delle Marche

Address

Università Politecnica delle Marche, Via Brecce Bianche - Ancona (AN) Italy

- Other working experiences -

Position held Position held (03/11-09/12) Cashier @ SNAI S.p.A - Civitanova Marche (MC) Italy (06/06-09/12) Sea Lifeguards @ Cluana Nantes - Beach Rescue

Position held

(09/08-07/10) Swimming instructor @ Soc. Coop. Sportiva Dilettantistica 'Il Grillo'

Education and training

October 2012 - April 2015

Name and type of education institute Principal subjects/occupational skills covered

University of Pisa - School of Engineering

Master's degree in Biomedical Engineering: Biomedical Signal and Image Analysis, Analogic and Digital Electronics, Minimally invasive devices, Bioinformatics (Python), Databases (SQL, HTML, BMF), Android, Diagnostic instrumentation (RX, CT, PET, SPECT, MRI)

Title of qualification awarded Thesis title Master's graduate in Biomedical Engineering - Final mark: 110/110 cum laude New methods for direct estimation of kinetic parameters from dynamic PET images.

Dates

October 2008 - December 2011

Name and type of education institute Principal subjects/occupational skills covered

Università Politecnica delle Marche - Faculty of Engineering

Bachelor's degree in Biomedical Engineering: Mathematics, Physics, Informatics (C++, SQL), Chemistry, Bioengineering, Electronics, Mechanics, Automation, Physiology, Biomechanics, Electromagnetism, Biomaterials and Bioinstrumentation.

Title of qualification awarded Thesis title

Bachelor's graduate in Biomedical Engineering - Final mark: 109/110.

Analysis of the changes of locomotion patterns due to treadmill walking.

Other training experiences -

Title of qualification awarded Title of qualification awarded Title of qualification awarded June 2008 - Swimming instructor license June 2006 - MIF - Surf Lifeguard - FIN-067582

May 2006 - European Computer Driving Licence (ECDL)

Period abroad

Dates

August - September 2007: 3 weeks period

Place

Regency College, 61 Western Road, Brighton and Hove, E. Sussex, UK

Purpose

"Progetto Ulisse 2007": language training funded by the province of Macerata through public announcement of selection

Dates

March 2007: 1 week period

Place Purpose United Nations International Headquarters and the Hilton New York, New York City, USA

National High School Model United Nations (NHSMUN): simulation project where students work as accredited delegates in committees of the Organization: they are called upon to analyze the main themes on the agenda of the UN, identifying themselves with the country represented and negotiating proposals and solutions with delegates from other countries.

Publications

[3]

[4]

[1] Santarelli MF, Vanello N, **Scipioni M**, Valvano G, and Landini L. "New Imaging Frontiers in Cardiology: Fast and Quantitative Maps from Raw Data." Current Pharmaceutical Design, March 28, 2017. doi:10.2174/1381612823666170328143348

[2] Santarelli MF, Della Latta D, **Scipioni M**, Positano V, and Landini L. "A Conway-Maxwell-Poisson (CMP) Model to Address Data Dispersion on Positron Emission Tomography." Comput. Biol. Med. 77, no. C (October 2016): 90–101. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compbiomed.2016. 08.006

Scipioni, M., Santarelli, M. F., Positano, V. and Landini, L. (2016). "The Influence of Noise in Dynamic PET Direct Reconstruction", in E. Kyriacou, S. Christofides and C. S. Pattichis (Eds.), XIV Mediterranean Conference on Medical and Biological Engineering and Computing 2016 (pp. 308–313). Cham: Springer International Publishing. http://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-32703-7_61

Scipioni, M., Santarelli, M. F., Giorgetti, A., Positano, V., Fucci, S. and Landini, L. (2016). "Pharmacokinetic analysis of dynamic PET data: comparison between direct parametric reconstruction and conventional indirect voxel-based estimation", Poster presentation at European Molecular Imaging Meeting (EMIM 2016). http://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.1.2194.2162

Meetings and conferences

Proceeding's title
Authors

Conference name and location

Proceeding's title

Authors Conference name and location

Proceeding's title Authors

Conference name and location

Kinetic compressive sensing: improving image reconstruction and parametric map estimation **M. Scipioni**, M.F. Santarelli, L. Landini, C. Catana, D.N. Greve, J.C. Price, and S. Pedemonte Athinoula A. Martinos Center's Scientific Open House, Boston, USA, May 25, 2017

Pharmacokinetic analysis of dynamic PET data: comparison between direct parametric reconstruction and conventional indirect voxel-based estimation

M. Scipioni, M.F. Santarelli, A. Giorgetti, V. Positano, S. Fucci, and L. Landini European molecular Imaging Meeting (EMIM 2016), Utrecht, The Netherlands, March 7 - 11, 2016

The Influence of Noise in Dynamic PET Direct Reconstruction

M. Scipioni, M. F. Santarelli, V. Positano, and L. Landini

XIV Mediterranean conference on Medical and Biological Engineering and Computing (MEDICON 16), Paphos, Cyprus, March 31 - April 2, 2016

Research projects

Dates

October 2014 - April 2015

Type

Master's thesis

Project title Topic

New methods for direct estimation of kinetic parameters from dynamic PET images

The algorithm subject of this work aims to combine into a single formula the operations of reconstruction and kinetic analysis of dynamic PET data: working directly on the projection data can improve both the quality and the speed of the resulting estimate. We presented a software implementation by which we could evaluate, via Monte Carlo simulations on an homogeneous test phantom, its performance in different SNR conditions. Subsequently, simulations of realistic phantoms were carried out to reproduce the behavior of anatomical sections of interest (thoracic and cerebral). This led, ultimately, to a first exploratory test on real experimental data.

Dates

October 2014 - April 2015

Type

Individual university project

Project title

Android App Development

Topic

Design and realization of an android interface that allows users to (1) access a remote database of songs, (2) listen a preview of a few seconds and (3) confirm the purchase. After the transaction, the 'app' will create a text file (recipe) with the total cost, saving it in a dedicate folder of the SD card. Furthermore, the 'app' implements an its own music player.

Dates

October 2014 - April 2015

Type

Topic

Group university project

Project title

ICT & Life Science DataBase project and realization using Bio Medical Framework (BMF)

The project consists of the design and implementation of an application for the management of databases in the clinical setting. The final goal has been the design and implementation of a database application based on relational DBMS and related user interface, addressing issues of conceptual and logical design and documenting the architecture of the software developed. The web application has been developed through the use of the BMF.

Dates

July 2011 - December 2011

Type

Bachelor's thesis

Project title Topic

Analysis of the changes of locomotion patterns due to treadmill walking

AIM: To test the effectiveness of treadmill as a tool to help people injured to recover and regain ability to walk freely and, at the same time, as a gait analysis system. **METHODS:** The comparison covers spatio-temporal (speed, cadence, strade length), kinetic (angular movement of the knee joint) and electromyographic (contraction intensity, number and duration of muscle activations) characteristics. CONCLUSIONS: From a kinetic point of view we can assert the absence of statistically significant changes. By using sEMG to register muscular activity data, we advice some changes in temporal distribution of contractions and activations but, thanks to our statistical approach, we can again classify them as not so significant.

Dates

March 2011 - June 2011

Type

Individual university project

Project title

Ultrasound eco-tomography

Topic

The purpose of the essay is to make direct contact with the laboratory instruments and not only see it during exercises. Research topic is the ultrasound tomography that is studied starting from the physical principles of image formation, through the hardware used and the way those tomographic images are generated. The work end with an identification of the main criteria used for diagnostic interpretation of the produced images and main artifacts that one can encounter and which degrade the quality of the image.

Personal skills and competences

Mother tongue(s) Other languages Self-assessment European level(*)

English Spanish

Italian

English and Spanish

Understanding				Speaking				Writing	
	Listening Reading		Reading		Spoken Interaction	Spoken production			
C2	Proficient user	C2	Proficient user	B2	Independent user	C1	Proficient user	C1	Proficient user
A2	Basic user	A2	Basic user	A1	Basic user	A2	Basic user	A2	Basic user

^(*) Common European Framework of Reference (CEF) level

English

Test Of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL) - STN11416A - American Language Center, Florence - April 2016 - Grade: 105 / 120 - European Ivl: C2

Academic English and Presentation Skills - Interdepartmental Language Center (CLI) of the University of Pisa, June 2016 - European level: C2

First Certificate in English (FCE) - Cambridge English Language Assessment, June 2007 - European level: B2

Certificate level of English as a foreign language (Level B2) - Interdepartmental Language Center (CLI) of the University of Pisa, July 2014 - European level: B2

Spanish

Certificate level of spanish as a foreign language (Livello A1) - Interdepartmental Language Centre (CLI) of the University of Pisa, February 2015 - European level: A1

Social skills and competences

- I have developed and refined social, communication, group work and public relationship skills both in my sport and working activity in the field of competitive swimming, having to interact with people of very different ages, and in the organization and management of summer camps for children.
- The experience working as a lifeguard has sharpened my ability to handle situations where you need to interact with a large number of people in contexts, sometimes, of emergency, while being able to mantain control of the situation.
- Active listener and open, ready to learn from all those with whom I come in contact.
- Clear and concise (oral communication), precise and attentive to detail (in writing).

Organizational skills and competences

- Leadership (I had the opportunity to lead different groups of students during academic projects).
- Attention to detail.
- Ability to work both independently and in team.
- Logistics and events organization capability, developed during my activity within the Cultural Artistic Association "Vox Dei Art", based in Morrovalle (MC), Italy.
- Self Motivation.

Technical skills and competences

- Ability to analyze the results of tests conducted.
- Ability to conduct researches aimed at solving clinical problems.
- School knowledge of human anatomy and physiology
- Able to analyze medical documents and complex technical and scientific publications in the biomedical sector

Computer skills and competences

Operative systems: Windows (very good); Linux (good)

Programming: good Word processing: excellent Spreadsheets: good Database: very good Web sites design: good

Programming language(s):MATLAB(very good), Python(good), PL/SQL(very good),

HTML(good), CSS(good), C++ (basic), LaTeX (excellent), Android(good)

Known softwares: MATLAB, Office, BioMedicalFramework, MathCAD, Eclipse

ECDL (European Computer Driving License): Yes

Artistic / sports skills and competences

Due to my artistic training (I studied piano for eight years with private weekly lessons), I was able to refine and improve my musical, technical and expressive skills, which until 2012 I exercised within the Cultural Artistic Association "Vox Dei Art", based in Morrovalle (MC), Italy.

I have practiced swimming at a competitive level for nearly 15 year, until 2010, receiving awards at regional and national level and receiving the "Athlete of the year" award from the mayor of Civitanova Marche (MC), Italy, in 2008.

Other skills and competences

I like to dedicate myself to amateur editing of images and / or video, and to the creation of websites, putting into practice a bit of self-taught knowledge.

DECLARATIONS:

I declare that the information in this Curriculum Vitae is correct and true.

Date June 26, 2017

I authorize the use of these personal data for the purposes of review of my qualifications for any post or position for which I have applied, according to Italian Law 196/2003, and for no other purpose.

Signature Middle Park

Date

June 26, 2017

Signature Milliophin